<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: events | Cristian Planas]]></title>
  <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-10T12:33:25+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://Gawyn.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cristian Planas]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[me@cristianplanas.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A picture with Matz]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2013/09/22/a-picture-with-matz/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-22T22:08:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2013/09/22/a-picture-with-matz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I met Matz at <a href="http://www.baruco.org/">Baruco</a>!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/cristianplanas-blog/me-and-matz.jpg" title="A picture with Matz" alt="A picture with Matz at the BaRuCo 2013"></p>

<p>By the way, you should watch his keynote. The best moment: "Designing a language means programming programmer's mind. So I designed a language that programmed you. I brainwash you!" (16:35).</p>

<p><div class="embed-responsive-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/6vdum5aXew8 "></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Barcelona Facebook World Hack]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/09/20/barcelona-facebook-world-hack/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-20T12:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/09/20/barcelona-facebook-world-hack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Facebook organizes some events, the Facebook World Hacks, to evangelize developers with its newest features. Some days ago it was the turn of Barcelona, and I was able to assist.</p>

<p>The day started with some talks, where some Facebook employees presented all the features of the Open Graph: that was pretty convenient, as I am developing right now the Graph integration of <a href="http://playfulbet.com">Playfulbet</a>.</p>

<p>After the talks, the Hack itself started: all the developers there had to create teams and start building an application using the Graph. There was even some prizes for the best ones.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/cristianplanas-blog/fb-world-hack-barcelona.jpg" title="Activities in the Barcelona Facebook World Hack" alt="People played ping-pong in the Barcelona Facebook World Hack"></p>

<p>Unfortunately, most of the assistants were PHP developers, so I decided to leave a bit earlier, without participating in the Hack. Sometimes I wish that Ruby was more mainstream!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BaRuCo 2012 review]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/09/11/baruco-2012-review/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-11T15:56:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/09/11/baruco-2012-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I was able to assist to the <a href="http://www.baruco.org/">Barcelona Ruby Conference</a>, organized by our friends of <a href="http://www.codegram.com/">Codegram</a>. The list of speakers looked very promising and the event didn’t disappoint anyone.</p>

<p>First of all it's important to remark how amazing the organization was: all the attendants were really well treated. In the picture below, you can see the delicious breakfast that we were able to enjoy just before the first speakers started:</p>

<p><a href="http://tweetmovies.net"><img class="center" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/cristianplanas-blog/baruco_breakfast.jpg" title="Breakfast at BaRuCo" alt="A delicious breakfast for the BaRuCo attendants"></a></p>

<p>But the main point in any conference is the quality of the talks, and BaRuCo speakers did a real good job: the quantity of the talks was small compared to other conferences, but most of them were really interesting. Some of them were slightly too technical for the audience who approaches for the first time the topic that is exposed, but most of them found the perfect middleground between depth and simplicity. However, there were some that stood out...</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Bronze medal for...</strong>: <em>Programming workout</em> by Michal Taszycki. A description of how to get from beginner to master in any discipline, with some useful techniques for improving in any area. I really like this kind of talks with a broader, more humanistic scope.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Silver medal for...</strong>: <em>Micro-Service Architecture</em> by Fred George. I already praised in this blog <a href="/blog/2012/02/05/programmer-anarchy/">another awesome talk given by Mr. George</a>: he is a really gifted speaker. This time, he exposed how his company faced some difficult cases dividing the architecture in multiple applications, managing to reduce the complexity of the solution.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Gold medal for...</strong>: <em>Why Agile (A short history of software engineering, and other ideas that didn’t work)</em> by Paolo Perrotta: I was a big fan of Mr. Perrotta since I read Metaprogramming Ruby, a book which changed the way I understand developing; but now… fuck, everybody in the congress fell in love with him. He stole the show with a great and very funny talk about how the own concept of software engineering is a misunderstanding of our craft.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Summarizing, looks like that Barcelona has a new you-can't-miss-it event. We are already waiting for 2013 tickets.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In a Vim Workshop]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/09/05/in-a-vim-workshop/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-05T05:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/09/05/in-a-vim-workshop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Long time without any update! I will try to be more perservering with my posts from now on.</p>

<p>In the next weeks I will explain some of my new projects, describing some of the difficulties I had to face and how I solved them. Mainly, issues with the architecture of a social sport betting application and a gem that I developed for it. But this won’t be today.</p>

<p>What I would like to explain today is how Drew Neil, the creator of <a href="http://vimcasts.org">Vimcasts</a> and author of <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/dnvim/practical-vim">Practical Vim</a> ran a Vim Masterclass at Itnig HQ, where I work. It was more than one month ago, but it was so cool that it is worth to write about it after so much time. :P</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/cristianplanas-blog/drew_neil_and_me.jpg" title="Drew Neil and me" alt="With the creator of Vimcasts"></p>

<p>Talking about the workshop, my impression was very positive. As always with Vim, I really feel that I am using only a very small part of its amazing features. The workshop proved me right (about my own lack of skill, but right): Vim is as flexible as you want it to be, and it gives you the possibility to -as Neil’s book tells- “edit text at the speed of thought”.</p>

<p>PS: This weekend <a href="http://www.baruco.org/">Baruco</a> starts. I will be there, and I hope to tweet quite a lot about it. Follow <a href="https://twitter.com/crplanas">@crplanas</a> on Twitter!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Programmer Anarchy]]></title>
    <link href="http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/02/05/programmer-anarchy/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-05T13:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://Gawyn.github.com/blog/2012/02/05/programmer-anarchy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="http://rupy.eu/">Rupy 2011</a>, I assisted to some very interesting
conferences, like the ones by <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/josevalim">José Valim</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/wycats">Yehuda Katz</a>.
 But the conference I remember the most is, by far, Programmer Anarchy.</p>

<p>In it, <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/fgeorge52">Fred George</a> exposes with a great amount of humor a development
process where programmers are not just developing the application, but
designing and modifying it beyond the customer's expectations. He
also reasons the need of removing certain roles (most of them, actually)
that don't produce code in the development process. As the popular agile (or antiagile?) manifesto says...
<a href="http://programming-motherfucker.com/">Programming, Motherfucker!</a></p>

<p>Personally, I have always thought that developers should take a more
active role when discussing the application with the customer: how many
times have we ended coding some feature that we knew for sure that was
stupid? We have to remember that, in the end, we are fucking technology
experts, specially compared to most of the clients (yeah, not being too
humble now). We should be stakeholders, and not minor ones, of our own
projects.</p>

<p>Here you can watch the conference. I would recommend it, even if you are
not very interested in the topic. If you know the IT world, it's really
hilarous:</p>

<p><div class="embed-responsive-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/32447325 "></iframe></div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
